Ben la charla de hoy la que esta procera ora is bueno a
In pagetar los atos como sifaran software
But our kick us up on Zurgi de a ser facil accessos a todos
Pero por todado también a in workshop que más traciendo que se chamos california code rush que
just a naciendo un
California civic data coalition is un projecto nuevo don de tratan de ser más facil accesso a
Sierto sata sets que pública el estado california
I believe you can the chile a con the chile a de que esta al workshop. He wanna
Enrado como a no datos sabiertos de california
So que tine por lo a pensago a no que tine con sotros y porque alguieniría esa workshop purpose
En presente dar que bueno cuando lo esto quie un poco aben y entendique en era
I think a person in tresante, but baris que el workshop bastar muy bien porque el
Para bessar pienza pienza estos a todos y pienza projecto muy como eso for liberios a todo una parte
Bueno intendar como afunciado un projecto eso for libero
Pero un muy muy tiempo un parce que muchas días de esta projecto que
Bueno estempezando pero a ralmente tambujo por gente como mucha polenda
Parse que hacer muy enteresante en tener que puedemos verde eso y ralmente
chonofu
Intender in bulucras el workshop entender que lo que estan haciendo ocho para barque
Lo que nosotros puedemos trigar para ca. Me parce que esta bueno juar air me terce y me terce bueno
con los a todos de california. Es un trigamuchos tiques para ar asoluar
¿A cosas grande se piasos de códio, hay documentación. Me parce que esta bueno
Esta las ocosas esta char la el workshop, muy ralacinales, me parce que despose de barla
char la, lejos interesar y ral workshop
All right, thank you. It's hard if I just take this out, walk around like this. Hello. How is everybody?
Hi
My name's Ben. That's me. I'm working on my Argentine beard. You know, it can't be too thick, right?
It's just got to be a little scratchy. That's how I fit in here. Kind of work on that. I
sometimes go by pale wire online and I'm here visiting you from Los Angeles, California where I work at the Los Angeles Times
which is a daily newspaper and 24-hour website and I work on a team there called the Data Desk and
We're a group of nerds that try to take data and turn it into news where what some people now call data
Journalists other people used to call computer-assisted reporters. Some people might call hacks and or hackers. We are it
We are you we are the people trying to do this stuff in a real American newsroom
and I'm gonna talk to you today about how we do things currently and how I think we as a group can maybe do things better and
The criticism that I've made put out is really self criticism as much as that of anyone else
All right, but before I begin I want to start with an apology
I'm sorry. My Spanish is so bad. I don't dare speak it in front of you. All right, I'm married to a Spanish speaker
She tries to encourage me to use it all the time
but really I'm about good at this as this guy and so I'm just going to avoid it and
I'm sorry, right now
I do live in Los Angeles where many people speak Spanish and most of it that I've picked up
I got eating lunch right at places like pinches tacos or no hodas
Cuban kitchen, but my wife has assured me that these terms are not fit for such an august audience as yourself
So I'm just gonna avoid it
Alright anyway, so if I'm talking too fast or I move too quickly and there's things you want to catch up with you can find all
the slides and the links for the things I talk about at this URL and
You can just hit that in so dub, you know, this is HTTP bitly blah blah blah got it
We ready?
Okay, let's go. I don't got much time. All right one. Okay, so how do we do data journalism today in my opinion?
Not really. Well, right. So where does it begin? It begins oftentimes with the government, right?
They have some valuable data about something that they're up to that we want to get at
Understand write about and probably say something nasty about so that they fix it, right?
So we go to them and we say at least in America
We can say I can write a letter and I can say dear government
Please send me every piece of data that you have on this topic and this is a real letter
I wrote and I send it off in the mail or attached to an email which is really kind of a weird thing a letter attached
An email. Why do we do that?
But we do because I don't know and then am I supposed to get the data, but I don't a long period of time goes by
I have 10 or 20 other emails. These are real ones. There's an extended negotiation
We what are we really gonna get? Am I gonna have to pay for it? How's it gonna happen? What's gonna do?
Right then ultimately Wow one day a CD arrives at my desk or in the mail and inside of it is a crazy government database with
No documentation and dozens of tables and so much data that I can barely understand it
And then I then spend days or weeks
Puzzling and trying to figure out what is in this database and how does it work and can I find anything or understand it?
Or what's going on and in that process?
I might meet someone like this the government employee responsible for creating that database who no one has ever asked how it works
And he's so excited to tell me and we have long conversations and I get to learn a little more about it
And I write really bad computer code
This is real
this is by me that just like tries to pull out that data and move it around and try to find what's going on in
It and I'm still lost and more days and weeks go by and I don't know what's happening
And then my editor very polite and then I'm totally confused and just lost and my editor calls me into her office
And she's like, well, you know, why do you work here again?
And what's really happening and shouldn't you be producing something that we can actually publish at some point at which point I then freak out
I get out my machete and I start hacking at the data and like trying to find something out of it and then in that
process I like create something like maybe a graphic and some stories and this thing we're gonna say and then
Whoo, I get across the finish line and we finish it and it's done and I'm just like, oh my gosh
we finally got there and I never would ever think about or talk about the state again and all that computer code and
all that work and
Everything that I learned in that whole process. Where does it go?
Right there
right and I go back to the beginning and I find a new topic and a new government person to pick on and a whole new
Process to begin again and all that stuff that I learned that was really really valuable
Most of it ultimately gets lost and this is really dumb
right and I do this and many of my colleagues do this and I think people in this room do this and it's kind of part of
our like news culture that
In when it works fine when you're just doing a story in one day and you can throw it away and starting in the next
But when you're doing really complex data work on databases that we revisit again and again
And that everyone uses and we're writing software
It starts to stop making sense
And so, you know
I think we need to as a group start being a little bit less like hacks and a little bit more like hackers, right?
If we're going to be writing software
And you know, it's there is some good news people are getting a lot better at it
Largely, I think thanks to a really great website and technology called git and github
Who here is using git and version control when they write their code a?
Lot of people that's good. It should be everybody right?
It should be unacceptable to work on our field without doing it and more and more people are and like that means as you're doing that
Story and writing that code every little change you write gets saved
so that you can walk back and understand everything you did and it all gets recorded permanently and it never gets lost and
500 straight SQL queries or six Python scripts that got ran and who knows what order at what time and have totally strange names and
Tucked into some bizarre folder with weird names that have like dates in the file names and all that crap, right?
This really helps you get past that a lot of people are then also using it to publish the data that they use as their
Analysis online, which is really great
And then even some people who are total overachievers are then taking the code that helped create their analysis
And they're putting it on github so people can kind of walk back and see what they're up to
And this is great for accuracy. It helps us not make mistakes by being more careful about the code that we write. It's great for
Transparency because it helps us
Be held accountable and for our readers to see what we're doing and build our credibility and maybe avoid some mistakes that way and know
That we're being watched which is also good
And it's great for reproducibility as well in a scientific sense that someone could take our methodology and our systems and be able to recreate
We're doing no good and people are doing this now and more and more doing it and that's a good thing and we should
Be pretty happy with ourselves, right?
This is like something that the science journals and people in other fields feel like they're behind and journalism is doing good
But there's like one problem if you go to any of these repositories
You know not to pick on anyone in particular
But I looked at a whole bunch of them preparing for this talk where people in our field are posting their code and saying oh
I'm so open and this is the open source and let's build the community
What do you see at each one of those when you check them out you see this?
Right, and if you're not a github user, it might not make sense
But the website with your code has some very simple metrics. How many people have contributed to this code?
How many people are interested in it?
How many have made their own copy and have worked on it?
And what I think we find with almost all the open source that our news people are putting out related to stories is you're seeing
very very little
contributions
Right or community building around these topics?
and
There's some reasons for that right which I think we should we should think about and understand because there's no
What is the difference between the ghost town?
That we put online and the trash can that we had before really not much you get some of those scientific benefits of transparency
and accuracy and
reproducibility
But you don't get any kind of benefits of the code
Contributions and the community building of a true open source project
Right and so you end up being Atlas working alone. Just like you were before
So how do we get better we get even nerdier? I think so. Let's like let's look at
Let's just look at a basic open source project and see how it works. Okay, so let's learn from the nerds
So if I go to github and I look at a thing called requests, is anyone used requests?
This is a python library
Right and it does what does it do so first off I can go to my terminal you could do this right now
And I can use a tool called pip which installs package software, right?
So this is a tool on almost all you know, you know computers or can be installed on most computers
Which will go into the cloud and will install software that's pre-packaged for you to use with one line
So it's very easy to get
Right. I don't have to go and read your Python notebook or find some weird thing or whatever
It's there in a centralized repository and with one command. I can install this piece of software
Then I can jump down into my Python terminal and I can now import it and use it. I'm now writing Python. I
Can I can then tell it to to to go get a URL and return it and that's all this library really does is you say
Hey, here's a URL something on the internet. I want you to go get it
It can do more than this, but this is the basics and then it returns a response and that's really all this thing does
That's not as exciting as an investigative story or something more complex
But guess what? It's what people want and it's what people will collaborate on look at this
38 million downloads of this one simple library, right?
And why is that because it does one thing and does it well one of my favorite nerd acronyms ready does one thing and
Does it well, which is also known as the eunuch eunuch philosophy and it's really a Lego, right?
It's a component of a work when strung together with ten other open source libraries or other things that another developer
Not you part of your story
But maybe future you right can use to build something that they want to do and the code that we're putting out
Oftentimes related to our stories and work is more like this the Cathedral here in Buenos Aires, right?
So instead of being a Lego, it's a cathedral, right? And what do you do cathedrals you go to worship and that's about it
Right, you don't go there to get work done
Alright, or build anything. So if we're gonna try to do that kind of thing in our field
What are our Legos, right?
What are the components of data journalism and the work that we do that might be possible for us to collaborate on?
And I think there's probably a lot of answers to this question. But one that I think is potentially
Interesting is data sources, right?
So there are out there in our world of journalism certain data sources that we return to again
And again and become almost like beats or topics that we're covering right what's copying the data and that can be
Election results public opinion polls. Sorry for the clipart guys
Crime reports, you know what's happening on Wall Street the census school starts
But you know here in Argentina the blue dollar which is one of my favorite phrases I've learned, right?
There's actually a Twitter account right that just tweets the blue dollar at me every day, which I started following just very cool
And each of these are data sources that are consistently updating have some schedule are structured are gigantic and that
Reporters in different ways to pursue different ends to tell different stories are all mining all the time every day
Right and for every one of those data sources
Almost all the reporters have their own little script to do basically this go to the government get the data
Convert it, you know pull it down and save it and do something with it
Load it into a database and repeat right and this process is known in computer software as ETL
Right because they can make anything boring in IT
ETL stands for extract transform and load and it's a basic component of almost all data
journalism that all that many many news outlets are writing for all these same sources and
Everybody's creating their own different competing pipelines to go get that data. There's the Washington Post. There's the New York Times
There's La Nación, whatever you can you know, let's let's twist this metaphor as far as we can when instead I
Think it's possible for us as a community to get together and build big pipelines that are bigger better
Stronger right and then we all collaborate on so that we don't independently all spend all this time doing the exact same thing doing the boring
Part of our work. Why should we compete at downloading and unzipping database tables, right?
We should be competing at finding and telling stories and doing ambitious analysis and making a difference
So this sort of boring component of our work might be the kind of thing we can organize around I think so instead of say PIP
install requests
Why can't I do PIP install BA election results or PIP install blue dollar and very quickly have basic data
Sources and those basic scripts available to me as package software in the same way
I have all these other components and then those can be well-documented maintained and and and you know grow and get better with time
Right. There are existing projects that do this and I think they're all awesome and going in the right direction
And we should do more like them open states Treasury open elections
The data open knowledge foundation are all kind of moving in this direction
And it's also the inspiration for a project that I'm here to talk about this conference, which is called the California Civic Data Coalition
So, you know
It's a team of the LA Times San Francisco Chronicle Stanford and Center for Investigative Reporting and we're coming together
Around campaign finance data the state of California released the bulk database of all the money in California state politics
It's 76 tables
650 megabytes 35 million records and about about zero
You know clues on how to use it and no one does really good, California
Campaign finance analysis because it's too hard to unpack and work with this database
So why should we all slave separately and fail to work on it when we can come together and write code that will make it easy
For everyone to do it and broaden the pool that can happen
And so that's what our projects about you can see it on github and if you just google California civic data coalition
And I'm here at this conference to promote the project and to try to get people involved
We have an event. We call the California code rush
I'm here with hundreds of tickets related to this repository that can help make us improvements and push towards our
Push towards our next milestones
I have prizes stickers and t-shirts for people who get things done and there's ways anyone can get involved if you're a hacker looking on
Saturday for something of medium-sized to work on come talk to me
We can find something cool if you're someone who's never made a contribution to an open source project or use github before we have lots
A little itty-bitty ones that'll take you 10 or 15 minutes. I'll walk you through it
You'll learn how all this process works and get your feet wet and in real open source project
Okay, so you can find me later today at the media fair the workshops in the hallways anytime and all day at the hackathon
Alright, and that's basically it
You can find again more everything from this presentation here at packaged data
the more about the code rush here and you know, feel free to email me or bug me at any time about anything and
That's it guys